改编自乔治・贝尔纳诺斯小说
From the Novel by GEORGES BERNANOS
参考译林出版社《一个乡村教士的日记》翻译
一个乡村神父的日记
DIARY OF A COUNTRY PRIEST
编剧 导演 罗伯特・布列松
Screenplay, Adaptation and Direction by
ROBERT BRESSON
我不认为这样忠实地记录下每天发生的事
I don't think I'm doing anything wrong
in writing down daily,
有任何过错
with absolute frankness,
这些生活中微不足道的秘密
the simplest
and most insignificant secrets
往往会失去它们起源的途径
of a life actually lacking
any trace of mystery.
昂布里库尔（法国加来省的一个小镇）
Ambricourt
这是我的教区 我的第一个教区
My parish. My first parish.
难道我必须要为了工作
Must I believe that it's only for duty's sake
隐瞒自己虚弱的健康状况吗
that I refuse to acknowledge my poor health?
自行车对我来说无疑是有用的
My bicycle is very useful,
但倘若我腹内空空 骑上坡路时就会头晕目眩
but I can 't ride uphill on an empty stomach without feeling faint.
我不再吃肉或是蔬菜
I deliberately cut out
meat and vegetables,
实在饿得昏头 才拿些面包蘸着酒果腹
eating only small quantities of wine-soaked bread whenever I feel dizzy.
我在酒里放许多糖
I add a lot of sugar to the wine.
面包也一直放到变硬为止
I let my bread harden
for several days.
多亏了这个习惯 我的脑子经常清醒
Thanks to this diet,
my head is clear,
身体也感觉强壮了些
and I feel much stronger.
法布雷加斯先生今天早上来到了圣器收藏室
Old Fabregars came to the sacristy this morning.
暂且不论我祷告所需要的报酬
Aside from the fee for my ti me,
天知道是什么
God knows, Mr. Fabregars,
我想您是希望能使用免费的布料
I 'd like you to have use
of the draperies for free.
我想是吧
I should think so.
不过是一堆碎布和补丁拼凑起来的东西
A lot of old moth-eaten rags held together by patches.
这些能花多少钱？
What could they have cost?
蜡烛得花不少钱
Candles are very expensive.
你自己就有
You do have a soft time of it.
没道理剥削我们穷人
There's no excuse
for exploiting the poor.
你可真是爱财如命啊 神父
You like your money easy, Father.
我们对所有人都是公平的
We charge everyone the same.
在我看来事情很简单
As I see it, it's simple:
我只求一件事
I ask one thing. It's only just.
让我可怜的妻子体面地下葬
Let my poor old wife be buried decently.
按普通流程来就行
The usual service.
所以我绝不会多付一个子 你明白了吗？
And for that I'll not pay
a penny more, you hear?
去拜访托西神父的时候 我依旧心绪不宁
I was still distraught when I went to see the priest ofTorcy.
上帝 我真希望像他一样身体健康 心情愉快啊
God, I wish I had his health and mental balance!
你应该把那家伙赶出去
You should have shown him the door.
把他赶出去 就是这样
Yes, shown him the door.
说起来 我认识这个法布雷加斯
Besides, I know Fabregars.
这老头很有钱
The old guy has plenty.
你们这些年轻的教士啊
You young priests!
你们这些年轻人现在还有什么风范吗
What have you young men got in your veins these days?
我那时代 人们培养的是教会人才
In my time they made men ofthe church,
教区的领袖 真正的首领
leaders of parishes, real masters!
现在教会派给了我们一些唱诗班小毛孩
Seminaries these days send us choirboys,
小叫花子 总是自以为做得有多认真
young ragamuffins who think they're working harder than anyone
其实他们什么事都没做成
because they never manage to finish anything.
碰到第一个难题
At the first sign of difficulty,
他们就哭哭咧咧说教区和他们想的不一样 乱扔东西发泄一通
they say the priesthood isn't what
they expected and drop everything.
我什么也不会摔的 我保证
I will not drop everything, I assure you.
在消除罪恶之外
Besides exterminating the devil,
你另外一个使命就是要做到受人爱戴
your other dream is to be loved for whoyou are.
但一个真正的教士是永远不会讨人喜欢的
A true priest is never loved.
教会才不会管你是不是受人爱戴呢 我的孩子
The church doesn't care a whit
whetheryou're loved, my son.
要受人尊敬 让人们听话
Be respected, obeyed.
守规矩 天天循规蹈矩
Keep order all day long,
但第二天 混乱无序还是会出现
knowing full well disorder will win out tomorrow,
因为在这个可悲的世界上 一个晚上就会把白天所有的工作付诸流水
because in this sorry world,
the night undoes the work of the day.
"天天循规蹈矩"
"Keep orderall daylong. "
当我在削土豆的时候
The priest of Torcy's words came back to me
托西教父的话回荡在我耳边
as I peeled potatoes for my soup.
我的助手从我身后过来了
The right-hand man came up from behind.
好消息啊 神父
Good news, Father.
是我能用上电灯了吗？
I'm getting electric light?
镇政委批准了你的请求
The council agreed to your request.
他们会负担费用 为您通上电的
It will install electricity for you at its own expense.
只是还需要走一些程序
There remain just the usual formalities.
会等很久吗？ 两到三个月 最多四个月就好了
- Will it take long? - Two or three months. Four at the most.
我很想和他谈谈他的卡巴莱歌舞
I'd have loved to tell him a thing or two about his cabaret.
他每周日都举办一次舞会
He puts on a dance every Sunday
称之为"家庭舞会"
and calls it "The Families'Ball, "
男孩子们在舞会上把女孩子灌醉
where boys have fun getting young girls drunk.
日安 神父
Good day, Father.
我没敢说
I didn't dare.
最单纯的事情无疑做起来应该最容易
The simplest tasks are by no means the easiest.
一个糟糕的夜晚
An awful night.
当我闭上眼睛 悲伤汹涌而来
As soon as I closed my eyes, sadness overwhelmed me.
这个早上 我做了所有我能做的 以表达我的同情和善意
I'd have done anything this morning
for a word of compassion or kindness.
我本非常期待教授教理课程
I was expecting a lot from catechism class,
孩子们正在准备圣餐礼
the children preparing for holy communion.
年轻的女孩子们使我感到希望 尤其是塞拉菲塔・杜孟谢尔
The girls had given me hope,
especially Seraphita Dumouchel.
圣餐礼是
Communion is
是 是传递
to re - to receive -
你来回答
How about you?
是用来传递
It's to receive -
通过圣礼上的圣餐传递耶稣的仁爱
Receive Jesus in the sacrament of the Eucharist.
那么耶稣是怎么创造圣餐的呢
And how did he establish the Eucharist?
为了创造圣餐
To establish the Eucharist,
耶稣掰开面包分给他的门徒们 说道
Jesus broke bread and gave it to his disciples, saying,
"拿来吃吧 这是我的身体"
"Take and eat. This is My body."
他拿起酒杯说道 "拿来喝吧 这是我的血"
He took wine and said, "Take and drink. This is My blood.
"你们应当如此行 为的是纪念我"
Do this in remembrance of Me."
今天的课就到这里 塞拉菲塔 过来拿你的成绩
That will do for today's class.
Seraphita, come forward for a good mark.
其他人可以走了
The others may go.
你急着希望见到耶稣吗？
Are you anxious to make your communion?
为什么不？
Why not?
反正它迟早会来的
It'll come soon enough.
你听得懂我上的课 也听得很认真
Yet you understand me, and you listen so well.
因为您的眼睛漂亮极了
It's because you have such beautiful eyes.
她们合伙捉弄了我
They had plotted it together.
为什么她们对我如此敌意？我对她们做错了什么吗？
But why such hostility? What had I done to them?
露易丝小姐天天来参加弥撒
Miss Louise attends holy mass every day.
如果她不来 教堂就一个人都没有了
Without her, the church would be empty.
她在庄园里担任家庭教师 那儿距我们这里有不少距离
Her position as governess at the manor
dictates a certain distance between us.
今天早上的时候 我发现她把脸埋入掌中
This morning she buried her face in her hands,
在祈祷的时候 我看到她脸上似乎是哭过了的神情
but at the blessing, I could see she'd been crying.
您一定非常孤独
You must feel very lonely.
夫人对我很好
Her ladyship is very kind,
但夏塔尔小姐并不喜欢我 对我呼来唤去的
but Miss Chantal enjoys humiliating me
and treats me like a servant.
她是你唯一的学生吗？
Is she your only pupil?
伯爵夫人有过一个儿子 但他死了 她很喜欢他
The countess had a son, but he died.
She adored him.
庄园里没人再提过他了
No one at the manor ever mentions him.
下个周四我会去转告伯爵的
I'll call on the count next Thursday.
拜访庄园的事让我忧心忡忡
This visit to the manor
has me quite worried.
如果能给伯爵留下好的第一印象
A good first impression could spell success for my plans
关于青年俱乐部和运动项目的计划 想必就能顺利一些了
for a youth club and sports program.
伯爵的影响力和财力能帮助我完成计划
The count's influence and wealth
could help me to achieve them.
(您需要的那块土地)平脊 粮仓也空空如也
The land is barren and the barn empty.
正是如此
That's true.
我不是要拒绝您 神父 但至少请给我点时间考虑
I'm not saying no, Father,
but give me time to think it over.
据说他对农民们很苛刻 他领土上也没有教民
He's said to be hard on his farmers,
and he's no model parishioner.
为什么他一下子变得如此吝啬？
Why has he so quickly become
the so desperately rare
他会是朋友 同盟 还是合作伙伴？
friend, ally and companion?
佩格雷奥特夫人会为您做好的 我已经告诉她了
Mrs. Pegriot will prepare it for you.
I've let her know.
我没有敢告诉他我的胃只能消化干面包
I didn't dare tell him my stomach only tolerates dry bread.
尽管这只兔子能抵上我付给管家半天的工资
I won't taste his rabbit stew,
我也无福消受
for which I'll have to pay the housekeeper a half day's wages.
我会托一个唱诗班孩子把它送给法拉特太太 她一定会高兴的
I could have a choirboy take it to old Mrs. Ferrant. She'd be delighted.
神父先生 我决定接受你的请求
Father, I approve of all your ideas.
噢 我的请求
Oh, my ideas.
但我提醒你 最好不要付诸实践
But I warn you against
putting them into practice.
我不明白
I don't follow.
这里的人们风气可不太好
The people here are malicious.
相信我 我知道的
Believe me, I know.
如果说要我给点建议的话
If I may offer a bit of advice,
我想 别动作太快
well, don't be in too much of a hurry.
别一下子就露出你的手段来
Don't show your hand at once.
没什么事是马上要办的 让他们先表现出来
Let them take the first step. There is no urgency.
只是那些都是我发自内心想做的
It's just that these things are dear to my heart.
在我的领土上
As for my land and my barn,
我不会阻止你的
I wouldn't discourage you.
等我们达到某些实质的认同的时候
We'll discuss them later
我们再来好好谈谈吧
when we get down to working out
something practical together.
你看去来气色不太好
You're not looking at all well.
你得多注意身体
You should take care of your health.
我的胃动不动就会发作
My stomach is very temperamental.
我有些迟疑 是否应该提到您的女儿
I hesitate, sir, to mention your daughter.
我的女儿？怎么了吗？
My daughter? What is the matter?
我想她十分不快活
I'm concerned about her sadness.
脸上始终闷闷不乐
Her face is far from cheerful.
她表情看起来沉重而僵硬
There is something hard and rigid in her expression
看起来不符合她的年龄
far beyond her years.
夏塔尔不高兴？你一定是在开玩笑
Chantal sad? You must be joking.
会不会是有人触怒了她呢？
Could someone be rubbing her the wrong way?
或许她希望从露易丝小姐那儿得到更多理解
Would a little more understanding from Miss Louise -
你胡说
You're mad.
我提到了露易丝小姐显然使得伯爵非常不悦
The mention of Miss Louise's name seemed to upset him terribly.
为什么？
Why?
在得出结论后 我抓住时机
I seized the first opportunity to return to the manor...
快速返回了庄园
a decision I had arrived at quickly.
仆人很快就来应门
The servant was several moments in coming.
我很清楚我会遇到伯爵
I was sure I'd meet the count,
他通常星期三下午在家
who was usually at the manor
Thursday afternoons.
然而我却见到了伯爵夫人
But I met the countess instead.
我的出现一定使她十分惊奇
I must have surprised her.
我打扰到您了吗？
Am I disturbing you?
一点也没有
Not at all.
我知道她非常孤僻
I knew she was withdrawn
一直将自己封闭在对死去的孩子的回忆里
and entirely absorbed
in the memory of her dead child.
她走了过来 对着一张椅子示意我坐下
She approached, motioning to a chair.
看到您我就想 您来一定是有原因的
On seeing you, I felt you had come
with some purpose in mind.
不然还会是什么呢
None other than to pay a call.
这么说的话 您并不打算说出原因了
And that you also meant
to keep it to yourself.
我向您保证不是这样
I assure you.
那么是我理解错了
I see I was wrong.
您的教民们可让您非常头疼啊 神父
Your parishioners worry you
a good deal, Father.
然而这只是个小小的教区而已啊
Yet it's such a small parish.
仅仅在地图上显得小而已 夫人
Small on the map, madam.
你对被委以重任的事想必还很陌生吧
It's a strange task
you've been entrusted with.
是的 夫人
Yes, madam.
我们所知的生活只是多小的一部分啊
How little we know what a human life really is.
尽管来的时候我还感觉很正常
Though I'd arrived feeling fine,
突然我发觉我没法跟上伯爵夫人的谈话了
I found myself suddenly incapable
of holding a conversation
甚至无法回答她的问题
or even answering questions.
来的时候我确实走得很快
It's true that I'd walked very quickly.
遇到病怏怏的法拉特太太的时候 交谈花了我不少的时间
I'd lost a lot of time with the ill Mrs. Ferrant.
神父先生！上帝 这是怎么了？
Father! Heavens, what's the matter?
您看起来非常痛苦
You seem to be suffering terribly.
痛在哪里？
Where is the pain?
这里  我的胃
Here, in the pit of my stomach.
不过没事 一点没事
But it's nothing. Nothing at all.
原谅我 夫人 我必须得离开了
Forgive me, madam, I must take my leave.
我病得十分严重
I'm seriously ill.
六个月前 我第一次遭受了病痛的袭击
I was first truck by this disease six months ago.
我去见了德尔本德医生
I went to see Dr.Delbende.
他是个老头 据说非常冷酷 现在已经退休了
He's an old man, rumored to be brutal, who's now retired.
托西神父让我来找他看病
The priest ofTorcy informed him I would be coming.
他用厚实而并不干净的手摸了摸的我胃部
He palpated my stomach at length
with thick and unclean hands.
他刚刚打猎回来
He'd just returned from hunting.
感觉不舒服的话就过来 记得给我打电话
When things get you down, come and pay me a call.
我不会告诉别人的 托西神父和我说起过你
I wouldn't say that to everyone,
but the priest in Torcy has spoken of you.
我喜欢你的眼睛
And I like your eyes.
忠实的眼睛
Faithful eyes.
一只狗的眼睛
Dog's eyes.
你 托西还有我都是一类人 古怪的一类人
You and Torcy and I are of the same race, an odd race.
和这些健壮的人是同一类人
The idea that I belonged
to the same race as these hefty men
这种事我从来没想到过
would never have occurred to me.
哪类人？ 靠得住的人
- What race?
- The race that holds on.
为什么靠得住？没人确切知道
And why does it hold on? No one quite knows.
还在读书的时候 我买过一辆摩托车
As a school boy I came up with a motto for myself:
"勇敢地面对它"
"Face up to it."
面对什么？我问你
Face up to what? I ask you.
不正义？
Injustice?
我可不是要到四处喋喋不休讲些关乎正义的事
I'm not one to go around babbling about justice.
我从没奢求过正义会实现在我身上
I don't expect it for myself.
我得问谁寻求正义？我不信上帝
From whom should I ask it? I don't believe in God.
我没什么经验
I'm not very experienced,
但我依旧能辨认出他语气里那种被深刻伤害过的声调
but I always recognize the tone
that gives away a deeply wounded soul.
不要太逞强了
You're not up to much.
看看吧
Just look at that.
谁都能看出来你食不果腹
Anyone can see you've not
always had enough to eat.
现在已经太晚了
Well, it's too late now.
还有酒精 那是什么情况？
And the alcohol - what about that?
酒精？
Alcohol?
当然不是说你酗酒
Not what you've drunk, of course.
是说远在你出生之前 就被喝下的酒
What was drunk for you,
long before you came into the world.
塞拉菲塔让我很忧虑
Seraphita worries me a lot.
有时候我想 她是不是很讨厌我
I wonder sometimes if she hates me.
她以超常的成熟折磨着我
She torments me with such exceptional maturity.
早上好 塞拉菲塔
Morning, Seraphita.
那天下午我归还了她的书包 然而她的家人待我非常粗鲁
I returned her book bag that afternoon.
I was received very roughly.
是的 我责备自己 祈祷得如此少而微弱
Yes, I scold myself for praying so little and so poorly.
然而我有时间祈祷吗
But do I have time to pray?
在去热思夫雷的路上 我遇到了托西教父
I met the priest from Torcy
on the road to Gesvres.
他让我搭车回到了教区住所
He gave me a ride back to the rectory.
除非主教急缺神父
The bishop must be hard up for priests
才会把一个教区托付给你
to put a parish in your hands.
我可以给你建议 但那又有什么用？
I could burden you with advice, but what's the point?
我做老师的时候就知道一些了不起的学生解开了最难的难题
I've known pupils who'd solve the toughest problems,
就像你这样 几乎是在泄愤
just like that, out of spite.
我哪里做错了呢？
Where have I gone wrong?
你太大惊小怪了
You're too fussy.
就像只被关在瓶子里的大黄蜂
Just like a hornet in a bottle.
但我认为你有一个祈祷者的灵魂
But I think you have the spirit of prayer.
修道士可比我们粗鲁多了
Monks are more shrewd than us.
另外 你几乎没有日常的常识
Besides, you have no common sense.
你的伟大计划只是空壳
Your great schemes don't hold water.
人们都知道 通常是说得越少越好
As for knowledge of men, the less said the better.
真诚地面对你的新教区吧
Face-to-face with your new parish,
不要装模作样的
you cut an odd figure.
所以呢？
And so?
所以？没什么 继续干呗
So? Well, carry on.
我还能说什么？
What else can I say?
又是一个糟糕的夜晚
A bad night.
凌晨三点 我提着灯笼来到了教堂
At 3:00 a.m., I took my lantern and went to the church.
我从没这么努力地祈祷过
I never endeavored to pray so much.
起先非常安静 平缓
At first quietly, calmly,
接着 一种近乎绝望的祈愿使我的心颤抖了起来
then with an almost desperate will
that made my heart tremble.
这天早上我收到了一封信 信纸看起来很廉价
This morning I received a letter
written on cheap paper,
并且没有署名
unsigned.
"一位好心人建议您能提出调换教区"
"A well -wisher advises you
to seek a transfer to another parish.
"越快越好"
The sooner, the better.
"我为您感到由衷的抱歉 但我必须重复: 快走"
I feel sorry for you,
but I repeat: Get out."
我发现了件奇怪的事
I made a strange discovery:
我认出了信的笔迹和它一致
The handwriting was identical.
另一个糟糕的晚上
Another terrible night.
雨下得如此之大以至于我不敢去教堂
It was raining so hard I didn't dare go to the church.
我无法祈祷
I couldn't pray.
我非常清楚 想要祈祷的愿望就是一种祈祷
I know very well that
the desire to pray is already prayer,
而上帝并不会要求更多
and that God couldn't ask for more.
但它并不是一种任务
But it wasn't a question of duty.
那时 我需要祈祷就像我需要空气
At that moment, I needed prayer
like I needed air in my lungs
血液需要氧气那样
or oxygen in my blood.
在我身后已经不再是熟悉的
Behind me, there was no longer
familiar day-to-day life
日日夜夜寻常的生活了
which one can leave behind in one fell swoop.
我的身后一无所有
Behind me there was nothing,
而在我前方 则是一睹隔绝的墙
and before me was a wall.
一堵黑色的隔绝的墙
A black wall.
突然间 仿佛有东西把我的胸砸得粉碎
Suddenly something seemed to shatter in my breast,
整整一个小时我都承受着这样的痛苦
and I was seized by a trembling that lasted over an hour.
如果这只是我的错觉呢？
What if it had only been an illusion?
连圣贤们都知晓他们有犯错 失败的时刻
Even the saints knew
their hour of failure and loss.
我在床脚边躺了下来
I lay face-down at the foot of my bed.
我只想彻底地表达接受
I only wanted to show complete acceptance
和投降
and surrender.
同样的孤独 同样的寂静
The same solitude, same silence,
然而这次 再也没有希望能穿越这层障碍了
but this time, no hope in breaking through the obstacle.
不 没有障碍物 什么也没有
There 's no obstacle. Nothing.
上帝已经遗弃了我
God has left me.
这点我已经确信
Of this I'm sure.
我并没有松懈
I haven't slackened in my duties.
我的身体不可思议地恢复起来 这让我工作变得轻松了一些
The incredible improvement
in my health makes my work easier.
德尔本德医生？你确定吗？
Dr. Delbende?
Are you sure?
德尔本德医生的尸体在巴赞伯爵的树林中被发现了
Dr. Delbende was found at the edge
of the woods near Bazan court,
他的头颅飞得很远 已经冷了
with his skull blown out,
already cold.
他滚进了一个边上排着一列树的土沟里
He rolled to the bottom of a tree-lined ditch.
人们推测他的枪卡在枝桠间走火了
It's thought his gun got caught in the branches
于是子弹飞了出去
and went off.
托西神父在他朋友的尸体边守了两夜
The priest from Torcy kept vigil for two nights by his friend's corpse.
他显然看起来非常悲伤
He was visibly anguished.
有流言开始传出 说德尔本德医生是自杀死的
It was rumored that Dr.Delbende had committed suicide.
你不认为德尔本德医生是
You don't think Dr.Delbende might have -
他非常沮丧
He was very disheartened.
他一直坚信患者们会回来找他看病
He believed up to the very end that his patients would return.
他的年轻的同事们四处流传 说他甚至不懂得防腐剂
His younger colleagues spread the word
that he knew nothing of antiseptics,
所以他的患者们都离开了
and his patients fled.
那些付费的患者 当然 不是其他的那些
The paying ones, of course. Not the others.
但事实是 他已经不再信仰天主教了
But the truth is he'd lost his faith
而他又无法停止他的信仰
and couldn't get over not believing.
我并没有权力听他这般推心置腹的话
I was in no condition to listen to his confidences just then.
它们如盐洒在了我的伤口上
They were like molten lead poured on an open wound.
我从未感到如此痛苦
I have never suffered so much
到死 我也不会再有这样的经历了
and likely never will again,
even when I die.
如果他真的是自杀
If he really killed himself...
你是否
do you think -
如果有其他人要问我这个
If anyone else were to ask me that!
我会回答 "只有上帝才能裁决"
God is the only judge.
德尔本德医生是个公正的人
Dr.Delbende was a just man,
而上帝正是公正的裁决者
and God is judge of the just.
不管怎么样 我们正在战争期间
We're at war, after all.
总得面对敌人
One must face the enemy.
"勇敢地面对它"就像他说的那样 你记得他的摩托车吧？
"Face up to it," as he used to say.
You remember his motto?
不 我并没有失去我的信仰
No, I haven't lost faith.
这一突然且残酷的考验
This abrupt and cruel or deal
也许震慑了我的神经和理智
may have upset my reason, my nerves.
但我的信仰仍在 我能感受到
But my faith remains. I can feel it.
我有所感觉 站起身来
I stood up with the feeling,
似乎听到有什么人在叫我
the certainty, that I had heard someone calling me.
然而我并不会发现任何人
Yet I knew I wouldn't find anyone.
你会信守诺言的吧？
You'll keep your word?
年轻的女士 我会按我说的去做
Young lady, I will do what I promise.
我惊呆了
I was overwhelmed.
我从来不懂得人们 我也永远不会懂得了
I know nothing of people and never will.
我跑去了托西神父那里
I ran to Torcy.
然而神父并不在家
Father is away.
没有个十天八天 他是不会回来的
He won't be back for eight or ten days at least.
我失望极了 只好靠着我身后的那堵墙
I was so disappointed. I had to lean against the wall.
您知道我不能在这儿接待您
You know I can't receive you here.
你承诺了要做的事
What you promised to do
你今天必须得做到
must be done today.
明天已经太晚了
Tomorrow will be too late.
她已经知道我去过您的住所了
She knew I'd been to the rectory.
她简直狡猾得像只狐狸！
She is as sly as an animal!
我曾经信任过她 当你习惯她的眼神
I trusted her. You get used to her eyes.
你以为她是善良的
You imagine they're kind.
现在我简直想挖出她的那双眼睛
Now I'd like to tear out those eyes of hers
用脚踩在它们上面 就像这样！
and stamp on them with my foot, like this!
你不害怕上帝吗？
Have you no fear of God?
我要杀了她！
I'll kill her!
杀了她 或者杀了我自己！
Kill her or kill myself!.
你不能呆在这里
You mustn't stay here.
只有一个地方 我才能听你说
There's only one place I can listen to you.
跪下
On your knees.
我不想忏悔
I don't want to confess.
你很清楚 我所要的只是公正
自从那个魔鬼般的女人来到我们家里
Ever since that beastly woman came to the house -
冷静
Stay calm.
我很冷静
I am calm.
我希望你像我一样冷静
I wish you could be as calm as I am.
那天晚上我听到他们说的了
I heard them last night.
我在他们的窗户外
I was under their window.
他们甚至都不拉上窗帘！
They don't even draw the curtains!
我知道他们想方设法要摆脱我
I know they'll get rid of me somehow.
下周二我就离开这里
I am to leave next Tuesday.
妈妈认为这样非常适合 也很实际
Mama finds it very proper and practical.
她居然说适合！简直好笑
Proper! It's enough to make you laugh.
她对他们所有的话都毫不怀疑
But she believes anything they tell her,
简直就像青蛙吞苍蝇
like a frog swallowing flies.
不要这样谈论你的母亲
Don't speak of your mother that way.
这样显得你并不爱她
You don't love her.
你甚至..  继续说 我恨她！You even -
- Go on. I hate her!
我一直都恨她
I've always hated her.
她是个傻子 还是个懦夫
She's a fool and a coward.
从来不会为自己的幸福起来反抗
Never could stand up for her own happiness.
你为什么要这样看我？
Why do you look at me like that?
让我一个人静一静
Leave me alone.
如果你爱你父亲
If you loved your father,
你就不应该这样反抗他
you wouldn't be in this state of revolt.
我对他已经没有敬爱了
I no longer respect him.
我恨他们 我恨他们所有人
I think I hate him. I hate them all.
我要报仇 我要跑得远远的
I'll get my revenge. I'll run away.
我要羞辱我自己 并且要让他知道
I'll disgrace myself and make sure he hears of it.
然后他就会和我一样痛苦
Then he'll suffer as I have.
从她的唇间我似乎能读懂
It seemed I could read on her lips
一些她并未明说的意思
other words that went unspoken.
你不能这么做
You'll do no such thing.
我知道那并不是真正让你生气的原因
I know that's not what's really tempting you.
把那封信给我
Give me that letter.
你口袋里的那封信
The letter you have in your pocket.
我所说的话我自己来承担
I said whatever came to me,
然而很奇怪的是 我能够确信我是对的
and yet, strangely enough, I was sure I was right.
把它给我
Give it to me.
她并没有坚持 把信交给了我
She didn't try to resist, and handed me the letter.
你一定是魔鬼！
You must be the devil!
致我的父亲（也可以理解为神父或上帝）
TO MY FATHER
我没有读那封信 就扔进了火中
I threw the letter into the fire, unread.
任何一个神父都不会如此发抖着遭受这样的苦难
Hers was a distress no priest
should approach without trembling.
在她的眼睛里 我看到了自杀的勇气
I thought I read suicide in her eyes.
但也许那只是转瞬即逝的冲动
But perhaps it was only a fleeting impulse
那种狂热才使它变得可疑
whose very fervor made it suspect.
我只是一个可悲的 无用的神父 别无其他
I was nothing but a miserable, unworthy priest.
我根本不该接待夏塔尔小姐 也不该听她说话
I shouldn't have received Miss Chantal or listened to her.
现在上帝正在惩罚我
God was punishing me.
我知道 一言既出驷马难追
I knew my words could not be taken back
而正是如此 我必须看着它走向覆灭
and that I had to see it to the end.
我害怕她会做出些冲动的事
I fear she may do something rash.
那是她被逼到绝路才会做的事
That's the last thing she'd do.
她非常害怕死亡
She's terribly afraid of death.
夫人 那可是想要结束自己生命的情绪啊
Those are the ones who kill themselves.
一定已经有人和你说过 "这种事在你的个人经验之外"
Someone must have told you that.
It's outside your personal experience.
你自己害怕死亡吗？
Are you yourself afraid of death?
是的 夫人
Yes, madam.
但是 我必须诚恳地说
But let me be quite frank:
自杀是很困难的
To die is difficult.
尤其是为了名誉
Especially for the proud.
比起我自己的死 我更害怕你们的死亡
I fear my death less than yours.
我丈夫想让谁留在这里都可以
My husband can keep whomever he likes here.
另外 那个家庭教师没钱养活自己
Besides, the governess has no money.
或许他是有些过于殷勤 太过亲近
Perhaps he's been too attentive, too familiar...
但我想 我不在乎
but suppose I don't care?
这些年各种各样的背叛
After putting up all these years with countless infidelities,
以及古怪的屈辱 我都尝过了
suffering absurd humiliations,
现在 我 作为一个老女人
shall I now, as an old woman -
已经顺从一切了
to which I'm well resigned -
而叫我睁开眼睛 撕咬争斗 抓住机会 有什么意思？
open my eyes, put up a fight,
take chances? Forwhat?
难道我得关心我女儿的荣誉比关心我自己的更多吗？
Shall I care more about my daughter's pride than my own?
让她自己承担自己做的事 就像我一样
Let her put up with it as I have.
夫人 请您小心点
Madam, be careful.
小心什么？
Of what?
小心谁？小心你？
Of whom? Of you?
不要夸大
Let's not overdramatize.
这些想法不会左右我的决定 我的过去没有什么让我羞耻的
Such thoughts don't dictate my conduct.
There's nothing in my past to blush about.
如果祈祷让我们懂得耻辱 那么它就是罪恶
Blessed is sin if it teaches us shame.
你只会说教！难道你是想让我担忧这些事吗？
Nothing but words! Are you trying to worry me?
你做不到 我会注意到的
Well, you won't.I have too much sense.
总之 我们所作所为都会受到裁决 我做错了什么吗？
Anyway, we'll be judged by our acts. What have I done wrong?
你把一个孩子丢出了她的家
You're throwing a child out of her home,
并且你明白那是无法挽回的
and you know it's forever.
那只是我丈夫的愿望
It's my husband's wish.
如果他错了
If he's wrong -
何况他相信她会回来的
He believes she'll come back.
你也这么认为？
And do you believe that?
上帝会惩罚你的       惩罚我？
- God will break you.
- Break me?
他已经惩罚了我
He has broken me already.
他带走了我的儿子
God took my son from me.
他还能对我做什么？
What more can he do to me?
我已经不再怕他了
I no longer fear him.
上帝只是暂时带走他
God took him away for a time,
而你的铁石心肠
but your hardness -
住嘴
Silence.
不 我要继续说
No, I will not be silent.
你心肠如此冰冷 你永远都无法再接近他
The coldness of your heart
may keep you from him forever.
这是亵渎！上帝从不复仇
That's blasphemy! God does not take revenge!
这不过是对凡人的说辞
Those are mere human words,
对你并不适用
with no meaning except for you.
你是在说我的儿子会恨我吗？
Are you saying my son might hate me?
你们再也不会有机会见到或者了解彼此了
You will no longer see or know each other.
没有任何罪恶会遭受这样的惩罚
No sin could make such a punishment just.
真是胡扯
This is madness!
这只是疯子的妄想
A sick man's dreams.
当我在这位蛮横的女人面前 无力地靠在身后的墙上时
With my back against the wall before this imperious woman,
我看起来简直像个罪人 正徒劳地为自己辩解
I looked like a guilty man trying in vain to justify himself.
也许我就是那样
Perhaps that's what I was.
你听到我说的话了吗？你听明白了吗？
Did you hear me? Did you understand?
不 夫人 我没有听见
No, madam, I didn't hear.
坐下 你现在没法去任何地方
Sit down. You're in no condition to go anywhere.
我说的是 这世界上没有任何一种罪恶会得到这样的惩罚
I was saying that no sin on earth could make such punishment just.
没有什么东西会将我们同我们爱的事物分开
Nothing can part us from those we have loved
比生活重要 甚至比救世还重要
more than life, more than salvation itself.
爱比死亡更强大 你的圣经就是这么说的
Love is stronger than death. Your scriptures say so.
我们并没有发明爱
We did not invent love.
它有它自己的规则
It has its order, its law.
上帝是它的主宰
God is its master.
他无法主宰爱
He is not the master of love.
他是爱的化身
He is love itself.
如果您懂得爱 就不要将自己置身于爱之外
If you would love, don't place yourself beyond love's reach.
真是疯了！你对我就像对待犯人一样说话
This is insane! You speak to me as you would to a criminal.
难道我丈夫的背叛
Do my husband's infidelities
我女儿的冷漠和逆反都不算什么吗？
and my daughter's indifference and
rebellion and hat red count for nothing?
你尽管斥责这些都是我的过错好了！
You might as well say it's all my fault!
谁都无法预先知道 谁能摆脱邪恶的念头
No one knows what can come
ofan evil thought in the long run.
我们身上隐匿的罪恶会污染空气 从而污染他人
Our hidden faults poison the air others breathe.
你要是抱着这种想法 你是活不下去的
You'd never get through the day if you dwelt on such thoughts!
我是这样坚信的 夫人
I believe that, madam.
我相信如果上帝赋予我们清晰的理念
I believe if God gave us a clear idea
让我们在善恶之间 紧密团结
of how closely we are bound to each other in good and evil,
我们的确是活不下去的
we truly could not live.
俯允赐教 这种被隐匿的罪恶是什么？
Pray tell, what is this hidden sin?
你必须顺从
You must resign yourself.
打开你的内心
Open your heart.
顺从？顺从什么？
Resign myself? To what?
难道我还不够顺从吗？
Am I not resigned?
如果我不顺从的话 我早就已经死了！
If I weren't, I'd be dead.
顺从？我已经太过顺从了！
Resigned? I've been too much so.
我真该杀了自己
I should have killed myself!.
我并不是说要放弃
That's not the resignation I mean.
那又怎样？我去参加弥撒
Then what? I go to Mass.
我想过要放弃一切宗教仪式 那和我不相称
I could have given up worship
altogether. Indeed, I thought ofit.
你怎么敢这样对待上帝
How dare you treat God like that!
我曾活得平静 我似乎已经在平静中死去了
I lived in peace, and I should have died in peace.
已经不可能了
That is no longer possible.
上帝对我来说已经无足轻重
God has ceased to matter to me.
你为什么再要强迫我承认我是恨他的 蠢货？
What will you gain by making me
admit I hate Him, you fool?
你现在已经不恨他了
You don't hate Him now.
你和他现在面对面Now at last you are face-to-face.
坦诚相见了
He and you.
你对我发誓     我不会发任何誓
- Do you swear -
- You can't bargain with God.
你可以无条件地屈服于他
You must yield to Him unconditionally.
但我能保证
But I can assure you
这世界上并没有天堂与地狱
there isn't one kingdom for the living and one for the dead.
只存在上帝的王国 不管死者还是活人 我们都包容于其中
There is only the kingdom of God, and we are within it.
在这一小段时间前 你知道我在想什么吗？
You know what I was wondering a moment ago?
也许我不该告诉你
Perhaps I shouldn't tell you.
我正在对自己说
I was saying to myself,
如果这世界上有上帝所无法掌控的地方
"If therewere, in this world orthe other,
some place free from God,
如果到达那里必须永远地遭受死亡 每一秒
if it meant suffering a death
every second, eternally,
我会带着我的儿子到那儿去
I'd carry my son to that place,
然后对上帝说道
and I'd say to God:
"尽管做你能做的最坏的事来惩罚我们吧！"
'Do Your worst and crush us!"'
这可怕吗？
Is that monstrous?
你是什么意思 不可怕？
What do you mean, no?
因为我也一样
Because I too...
有时也会这样想
have felt that way at times.
德尔本德医生的形象出现在我面前
Dr. Delbende's image was before me.
他那衰老却坚定的目光正注视着我
His old, unflinching eyes were on me.
那种我害怕注视的目光
Eyes which I feared to read.
如果哲学家与异教徒们也拥有上帝的话
If our God were the god of the pagans or philosophers,
尽管他也许会去最高的天堂中避难
though he might take refuge in the highest heavens,
我们的苦难也会将他唤回人间
our misery would drag him down.
但就像你所知道的的 我们的上帝并没有躲藏
But as you know, ours did not wait.
你能对他施以拳脚
You might shake your fist at him,
向他脸上吐痰
spit in his face,
用荆条鞭打他
whip him with rods,
最后将他钉在一个十字架上
and finally nail him to a cross.
那又有什么关系呢？
What would it matter?
已经结束了     我需要对他说什么话？
It is already done.
- What must I say to him?
说
Say:
愿您的王国降临
Thy kingdom come.
愿您的旨意施行
Thy will be done.
我做不到
I can't.
我仿佛已经失去他好几次了
It's as if l were losing him twice over.
您所愿望降临的王国既是您的也是他的
The kingdom whose coming
you have just wished for is yours and his.
那么就让这个王国降临吧！
Then let that kingdom come!
我就像我所做的那样仇恨并侮辱过上帝
I must have hated God to insult him as I did.
现在这种仇恨已经在我心中死去了
I might have died with that hatred on my heart.
一小时前 我的生活还井然有序
An hour ago, my life seemed to me in order,
所有事物都各就其位
each thing in its place.
您说的一切都没能在我这儿留下任何痕迹
You have left nothing standing.
就像您将生命交给上帝那样
Give it to God just as it is.
你没有理解
You can't understand.
你认为我是如此顺从
You think I'm so quickly meek!
我的骄傲依然会让我
The pride still left in me-
将您所有的傲气交出来
Give him your pride along with everything else.
把所有都交给他
Give Him everything.
真是疯了
What madness.
原谅我
Forgive me.
上帝并不是行刑者
God is no torturer.
他希望我们怜惜自己
He wants us to be merciful with ourselves.
我做的事已经定了 无法挽回了
What's done is done.There's nothing I can do.
愿平和与你同在
Peace be with you.
我必须立马离开庄园前往东巴斯勒
I had to leave immediately there after for Dom basle
到家的时候已经很晚了
and arrived home very late.
老花匠克洛维斯将一个小盒子交给了我
Clovis, the old gardener, gave me
a parcel from the countess.
是伯爵夫人给我的 我知道那是什么
I knew what was in it.
那枚小小的圣牌 已经空了 链子也已经坏了
The small medallion, now empty,
and its broken chain.
在那里面还有一封信
There was a letter as well.
"亲爱的神父 我对那个年轻的生命无望的回忆 "
" Dear Father, the hopeless
memory of one young child
"将我与所有事物隔绝开来 使我饱尝孤独"
had me isolated from everything
in a terrifying solitude,
"而现在看来 另外一个孩子将我从中拯救了出来"
and it seems as if another child
has drawn me out of it.
"我希望这样称呼您为孩子没有让您觉得屈尊"
I hope I don't hurt your pride by calling you a child.
"您是上帝的孩子 愿上帝永远这样呵护您"
You are one, and may God keep you so always.
"我自问着您为何要做这些事"
I ask myself how you did it,
"或者说 我不再自问了"
or, rather, I have ceased to ask.
"怎么样都好"
All is well.
"我并不相信顺从就能解决一切"
I didn't believe resignation was possible,
"事实上我从未真正顺从过"
and in fact it's not resignation that's come over me.
"我没有顺从过 而我感到很幸福"
I'm not resigned - I'm happy.
"我不渴望任何东西"
I desire nothing.
"今晚我必须得把这些想法告诉你"
I had to tell you these things this very evening.
"因为我们再也不会交谈了 对吧？"
We shall never speak ofthem ever again, shall we?
"永远不"
Never.
"这样很好 ‘永远不’ "
It is good, that word 'never.'
"在你所表达的话语里"
I feel it expresses, beyond words,
"我感受到了你带给我的平静"
the peace you have given me."
伯爵夫人在当晚去世了
The countess died last night.
我大汗淋漓地跑着来到了庄园
I arrived at the manor streaming with sweat.
伯爵假装没有看见我
The count pretended not to see me.
她从床上摔了下来 砸坏了夜桌上的东西
She fell out of bed, breaking objects on the night table.
是心绞痛 毫无疑问
Angina pectoris, no doubt.
她已经感到身体不适好几个月了
She hasn't been quite herself
for some time.
在她的脸上 我期待着能看到 也许是笑容On her face I had hoped to see -
I don't know-perhaps a smile.
但她并没有微笑
But she wasn't smiling.
当我抬起手为她祝福时 我的胳膊几乎抬不起来
My arm was like lead in raising it to bless her.
两点的时候我离开了庄园
I left the manor about 2:00,
教义课堂也比我预期结束得要晚得多
and catechism class ended
much later than I thought it would.
回家的路上 我看到长长的送葬车队
Upon returning, I found
a continuous parade of cars,
而庄园中满是窃窃私语的声音
and the murmur ofvoices filled the manor.
我本想整晚呆在伯爵夫人身边的
I'd have liked to spend the night at the countess 'side,
然而修女们在那儿守着
but the nuns were there,
而伯爵的舅舅卡侬先生要和她们一起 整夜守着伯爵夫人
and the canon, the count's uncle,
had decided to keep watch with them.
我并不敢坚持自己的愿望
I didn't dare insist.
我最后一次进入了她的房间
I entered her room for the last time.
那个下午我们争执的回忆
The memory of our struggle
如此清晰地让我回想起来 以至于我几乎要晕倒过去
came back so vividly that I thought I would faint.
我掀开了她脸上遮盖的薄纱
I parted the muslin veil
用手指摩挲她冰冷的前额
and brushed her forehead with my fingers.
我曾对她说过 "愿平和与你同在"
I had said to her,"Peace be with you, "
而她将跪着接受了这份平静
and she'd received that peace on her knees.
多么不可思议 人会将自己不曾拥有的东西作为礼物馈赠给别人！
What wonder, that one can give what one doesn't possess!
噢 我们空手所创造的奇迹啊！
Oh, miracle of our empty hands!
当我路过的时候我似乎听到了窃窃私语
I thought I heard murmuring as I passed.
他们似乎在谈论着我
They seemed to be talking about me.
您见过我的侄女吗？
You saw my great-niece here?
是的 加侬先生
Yes, Canon.
在这里 以及教堂
Here, and in the church.
她想引起您的注意 我毫不怀疑
She worked her way around you, I've no doubt.
不 事实上我对她十分严厉
I treated her harshly.
真的 我想我甚至伤害了她
Indeed, I think I humiliated her.
你认为你影响到她了吗？
Do you feel you influence her?
暂时还没有
Not at the moment.
但我想她不会忘记我曾反对过她 我不能欺骗上帝
But she won't forget I stood up to her
and that you cannot deceive God.
她和您的见面中得到的印象和您非常不同
Her version of your meeting is very different.
夏塔尔小姐为人高傲 早晚会为自己的谎言而羞愧
Miss Chantal is too proud
not to blush one day at such a lie.
她会感到羞愧的
She'll feel ashamed,
她需要感到羞愧
and she needs to feel ashamed.
那么你呢？
What about you?
噢 我
Oh, me...
你忽视自己的病情
You neglect your health.
我的胃很不好伺候
My stomach is very touchy.
它只能消化面包 水果和酒
It digests only bread, fruit, wine.
就您现在的状况 我担心酒对您只有害处没有好处
In your state, I fear wine
may do more harm than good.
幻想的健康并不是健康
The illusion of health is not health.
神父
Father,
关于教区的管理 我们之间也许没有一致的看法
there probably aren't two things
we agree on about how to run a parish,
但这是您的教区 您有权管理
but this is your parish to run as you see fit.
我只能听您的
One has only to hear you.
我并不需要知道您和去世的伯爵夫人之间发生了什么
I needn't know what happened
between you and the late countess,
但我希望能消除关于此的危险流言
but I wish to cut short some foolish and dangerous talk.
我的侄女正尽力地散布流言
My nephew is moving heaven and earth.
主教是个单纯的人 非常当真
The bishop, a simple man, takes him seriously.
她将你们的对话用一两句话概括给了他听
Sum up in a line or two your conversation of the other day.
我并不是想要揭露什么
I'm not asking you to be inaccurate,
因为我相信您 作为一个神父
still less to reveal anything
confided to you as a priest.
除了给主教过目 我不会拿去给任何人看
The paper won't leave my pocket except
to be placed before his grace's eyes.
您不相信我？
You distrust me?
我不知道这样的流言是如何产生的
I don't see how there could be
any report of such a conversation.
不可能有人目击到
There were no witnesses.
只有伯爵夫人自己才可能把这件事告诉别人
The countess alone
could give authority for that.
很好 不要再想刚才的话了
Very well. Let's drop the idea.
如果您愿意的话 我们明天再见
We'll meet again tomorrow, if you agree.
我想让您和我的侄女当面谈一下
I meant to prepare you
for your conversation with my nephew.
你不说那种满口空话的人
You're not one of those
who can speak and yet say nothing,
但不幸的是 那正是如此
but unfortunately that's what is called for.
我做了什么错事吗？他们有什么反对我的证据呢？
But what have I done wrong?
What have they got against me?
你做了的就是做了
That you are what you are,
什么也改变不了 我的孩子
and nothing can be done about that, my child.
人们并不恨你的单纯 恰恰相反的是他们要躲避你
People don't hate your simplicity -
they shield themselves from it.
你的单纯像火一样烤着他们呢
It's like a flame that burns them.
我按我所承诺来到了庄园
I went to the manor as I'd promised.
夏塔尔小姐来应门 这让我警惕了起来
Miss Chantal came to the door,
which made me suspicious.
她几乎将我推进了小客厅
She almost pushed me
into the drawing room.
百叶窗紧闭着
The shutters were closed.
伯爵夫人的扶手椅
The countess 'armchair
尾部烧黑了的原木 都还在那天的位置
and the blackened logs
were still in the same place.
年轻的女士 我时间并不多
Young lady, I've very little time.
我会站着说话
I will speak standing up.
为什么？
Why?
我的位置并不在这里 你的位置也不在这里
My place is not here,
and neither is yours.
你害怕死亡吗？
Are you afraid of the dead?
家庭教师今晚就走了
The governess is packing and leaves this evening.
你看 我得到了我想要得到的结果
You see, I get what I want.
这样的成就让你满足
Little good it will do you.
如果你一直保持这样 你总能找到仇恨的对象
If you stay as you are,
you'll always find someone to hate.
但你真正恨的人只有你自己
But the only person you really hate is yourself.
如果我得不到我想要得到的 我会恨我自己！
I'd hate myself the same if didn't get what I wanted.
我必须得到幸福！否则
I must be happy! Otherwise -
不管怎样 这都是他们的错
Anyway, it's their fault.
为什么要把我关在这个阴森森的地方？
Why keep me cooped up in this ghastly place?
血液明明已经在我的血管里沸腾 我却无法大声说出来
Blood pounding in my veins, but never allowed to raise my voice!
我还必须低声下气 整天只能专注在针线活上
Hunched all day over boring needle work, biting my tongue!
简直太可怕了
It's awful!
我能感觉到
That's when I can feel - I don't know -
有一种奇特的力量在我内心聚积起来
this extraordinary force building up inside me.
似乎用尽生命的长度也无法将这种热情消耗殆尽
Life itself won't be long enough to let it all out.
你自己这样的言行难道不觉得羞耻吗？
Aren't you ashamed of such chatter?
伯爵随后就从外面走了进来
The count arrived just then from the fields,
叼着他的烟斗 看起来非常自在
smoking his pipe
with a contented air.
我女儿把那份Has my daughter given you
我岳父葬礼的清单交给您了吗？
the papers from my father-in-law's funeral?
我想这次就照着那份清单上办
I should like this one to be the same.
她没给我      您没碰到她吗？
- She gave me nothing. - Didn't you see her?
神父在和我谈别的事
Father and I spoke of other things.
你应该交给他全权处理
You ought to give him a free hand.
那些繁文缛节都荒唐极了
All these complications are ridiculous.
您还得为家庭教师签张支票
You should sign the governess' check, too.
记得吗 她今晚就要走了
Remember she's leaving this evening.
她不呆到葬礼结束吗？
She's not staying for the funeral?
这样大家都会觉得奇怪的
Everyone's sure to wonder why.
觉得奇怪？
Everyone?
没人会注意到她的
I'd be surprised if anyone noticed her absence.
六个月的工资？简直荒唐
And six months' wages? That's ridiculous!
她应该好好休息一下
She deserves a bit of a break.
在这儿的日子可不有趣
Life here hasn't been much fun.
您的支票簿放在桌子上
Your checkbook is in the desk.
等会儿
Later, later.
随您的便
Very well.
我只是希望您不要特意去找她商量
I only wanted to spare you having to discuss it with her.
她心情不太好
She's quite distressed.
神父 我坦率地告诉您
Father, I may as well be frank.
我非常敬重神职人员
I respect the clergy.
我的家人和您前任的关系都很不错
My family's always been on good terms with your predecessors,
但仅仅是出于尊重和友谊
terms of mutual respect and friendship.
他们绝不会干涉我家的私事
But no priest shall meddle in my family affairs!
我并不是自愿插手您的家事
We get involved sometimes against our will.
您没有意识到自己已经不由自主
You have been unwillingly, or at least unknowingly,
造成了多大的不幸
the cause of a great misfortune.
我希望您不要再与我女儿交谈了
I don't wish you to speak to my daughter again.
我说了什么会导致不幸？
How have I caused a misfortune?
我舅舅一定对您说过了
My uncle must have explained.
我不赞成您的轻率举动
Suffice it to say that I disapprove of your indiscretions.
您的性格与习惯对教民来说是危险的
Your character and your habits are a danger to the parish.
我的习惯？
My habits?
祝您日安 神父
I bid you good day, Father.
伯爵夫人的遗体在今天早上下葬了
The countess was buried this morning.
她长久的痛苦已经功德圆满 而我的痛苦则刚刚开始
Her long ordeal is over. Now mine begins.
当我为她祈祷时 这种又愉快又恐惧的心情是从何而来的呢？
Where did that mixture of joy and fear
come from when I'd blessed her?
这种奇怪的柔情？
That strange tenderness?
她已经属于那个看不见的世界
She already belonged to the unseen world.
我的眼前下意识地浮现出她的眉头
Without realizing it, I'd glimpsed on her brow
她已然归于死的平静
a reflection of the peace of the dead.
对此必须应当付出代价
One must surely pay for that!
尽管我应该撕掉这些
Though I thought I must destroy those pages
狂热中写下的话语
written in a moment of true delirium,
然而我必须对我自己做出指控
yet I would bear witness against my own self
正是我遭受这难言的苦难
that my difficult ordeal,
我可怜的生命中最大的绝望
the greatest deception of my poor life -
我无法想到会有更痛苦的事
for I couldn't imagine worse -
我发觉我既不能顺从自己的欲望
found me lacking in both resignation
也没有足够勇气面对
and courage,
我想要--
and that I was tempted to -
您是来指责我的吗？    别孩子气了
- Did you come on my account?
- Never mind that, my boy.
如果我想指责你 我会这么做的
I do as I please.
你得稍微注意一下穿着
You should pay a little attention to how you dress.
比如说你这件披肩
That cape, for instance.
还有 注意你自己的身体
And then there's your health.
我对我的身体无能为力   你当然可以
- I can't control that.
- Yes, you can.
你的饮食习惯真是荒唐
Your diet's absurd.
是的 我必须和你好好谈谈你的饮食习惯
Indeed, I must give you a good talking to about that.
等你意识到问题的时候 你会吓一跳的
And you're surprised when you feel ill!
要是我像你这样晚才发觉 我会胃抽筋的
I'd get stomach cramps too if late as you do!
对于你的灵魂来说 其实也一样
As for the inner life, my lad, I'm afraid it's the same thing:
你没有好好为你自己祈祷
You don't pray enough.
你太痛苦以至于放弃祈祷了 我是这样认为的
You suffer too much to pray. That's how I see it.
但是 我不能祈祷啊
But I can't pray.
如果你无法祈祷 那就对着别人这样说吧！
If you can't pray, just repeat the words!
听着 我不觉得我看错了你
Listen, I don't think I've been wrong about you.
你试着回答看看
Try to answer this.
我对我们的职业思考了很多
I've thought a lot about vocation.
我们都接受上帝的召唤
We've all received the calling,
只是不同人方式不同
only not in the same way.
把事情简单化吧
And to simplify things,
我试着把我们置身于上帝的世界 像福音书里那样
I try to put each of us in his place - in the Gospels.
总之 我曾想... 幻想过 In short, I think-or I imagine-
如果 我们的灵魂能拖动躯体
if our soul could drag
this wretched body of ours
回到两个世纪前的洪荒之初
back up that slope of 2,000 years,
那么它会被引导到那个最恰当的地方
it would lead it straight to the very place where-
什么？怎么了吗？
What? What's the matter?
你在哭？
Are you crying?
我没有意识到自己正在哭
I hadn't realized I was crying.
在托西神父的话语中 我仿佛回到了橄榄园(耶稣受难前祈祷和被捕的地方)
The truth is that I always return to the olive grove.
一瞬间我感到熟悉 仿佛灵魂受到触动
It was a very familiar and natural movement for my soul.
而直到那时我才意识到
I'd never realized it until that moment.
突然间 上帝通过这位年老的神父口中
Suddenly, Our Lord had shown me grace
向我呈现了恩典
and revealed through my old master's lips
我所做的选择已经永远无法改变
that nothing would tear me from my chosen place in eternity.
我已然是这神圣的苦难的囚徒
I was a prisoner of the Holy Agony.
我不认为你是那样的人
I didn't think you were such a child.
你的神经会被粉碎的
Your nerves are shot to bits, my son.
好了 我们不要再呆在这儿了
That's enough, now. We can't stay here all day.
也许是上帝想要怜惜你呢
After all, maybe God means to keep you in misery.
但这并不会左右对我们的裁决
But trials never warp our judgment
当我们的灵魂受到质疑的时候when the welfare of souls is in question.
我已听说关于你的流言了
I've been hearing some disturbing things about you.
没关系 我知道人们是恶毒的
But no matter. I know how malicious people can be.
但你对待伯爵夫人也太蠢了...简直像出戏！
But the foolish way you dealt
with the countess - melodrama!
我不明白
I don't understand.
关于圣牌的那回事
That business with the medallion.
圣牌？
The medallion?
别傻了！有人看到了 没什么神奇的
Don't be silly! There was a witness.
Nothing miraculous about it.
谁看见的？    伯爵夫人的女儿
- Who saw us? - Her daughter.
你说那是顺从？
You call that resignation?
你强迫她把她儿子的遗物扔进壁炉里！
Forcing a mother to burn the one relic of her dead child.
简直像遗嘱上的故事！
It's like a story from the old testament!
还说什么永远的分离！
And to speak of eternal separation!
你不能这样要挟他人的灵魂 孩子
One doesn't blackmail souls, my child.
那是您所认为的 我可以告诉您
That's your version of what happened. I could tell a different one.
事实并不是这样
But it's essentially true.
你不能说得更详细些吗？
Is that all you can say?
是的
Yes.
不管怎样 不要再见那个女儿了 她是个魔鬼
Whatever happens, don't see
the daughter again. She's a demon!
我不会拒绝见她的
I won't close my door to her.
只要我还在这里做神父 我就不会拒绝接见任何人
I'll close my door to no one while I am the priest here.
她声称你和她最后打了起来
She claims her mother
fought you to the last,
你使她非常伤心 几乎发狂
and that you left her upset and spiritually distraught.
那是真的吗？
Is that true?
不是
No.
你抛弃了她
You left her-
我将她交给了上帝
I left her with God.
你对她的严辞也许让她死时受到了折磨
The memory of your harsh words
may have tormented her as she died.
她死得非常安详
She died in peace.
你怎么知道？
How would you know?
不管怎样 她已经去世了
In any case, she's dead now.
你还能希望人们能怎么想？
What do you expect people to think?
那样对于心脏有问题的人来说总不是好事
Scenes like that aren't good for someone with heart trouble.
我不是要引诱你说到那封信
I wasn't even tempted to speak of the letter.
我把它交还给区长了
I returned to the rectory.
我并不痛苦  甚至感到如释重负
Instead of suffering, it felt like
a great weight had been lifted.
与托西神父的会面就像
That meeting with the priest
from Torcy was like a rehearsal
即将与我的院长们会面的一次彩排
for those I was to have very shortly with my superiors.
我几乎高兴地发现 我并没有说什么过激的话
I'd discovered, with something bordering
on joy, that I had nothing to say.
两天以来 我一直担心会被指责做了些我并没做的事
For two days, I'd feared being accused
of something I hadn't done...
那样会让我无法保持沉默
and honesty would have forbidden me to remain silent.
而现在 我能让所有人判断我的行为
But now, I could let everyone judge my actions for himself.
我得到了解脱
I was very relieved as well
不再担心夏塔尔小姐对我
to think Miss Chantal could have been sincerely mistaken
和伯爵夫人的谈话产生任何遗漏而导致的误解
as to the real meaning of our talk,
which she may well have misheard.
我可怜的孩子！
My poor child!
原来是这样
So that's how it is.
我不明白怎么了 我什么也不懂
I didn't understand yet.
I didn't understand anything.
我想自己方才享受的片刻平静
Except that the strange peace I'd just enjoyed
也许只是一个新的不幸的预兆
was the harbinger of a new misfortune.
那根本不是酒 那简直是毒药
This isn't wine. It's some monstrous poison.
我只有这个
It's all I have.
你应该来问我要
You should have asked me.
如果我知道我会的 我发誓
I swear.
住嘴！看看你都喝了些什么 没死真是万幸
Silence! With that stuff inside you, it's a wonder you're not dead.
幸好我过来了一趟
I'm glad I came.
来 坐下
Come, sit down.
不
No.
我的声音像往常那样瑟瑟发抖
My voice trembled in my chest as it always did
内心的声音告诉我不能动摇
whenever something inside told me I had to stand my ground.
没有任何力量能让我坐下
No force in the world could have made me sit.
听着 我不是对你发火
Listen, I'm not angry with you,
我也不认为你酗酒
and I don't take you for a drunk.
我们这些乡下人
We country people of these parts
多少都是些酒鬼的后代
are all more or less drunkards' children.
德尔本德医生已经对你指出了吧
Delbende put his finger on the trouble right off.
你父母在你出生时就烂醉如泥
You were born pickled in the stuff, my poor friend.
我相信 你完全不知情
I'm sure you had no idea.
但你渐渐的也开始依靠酒来支持...什么酒呀！
But you slowly drifted into expecting
from wine - and what wine! -
也许你能从中得到些许勇气和力量
the strength and courage you might
have gotten from a good roast.
我提醒你的是 尽管你并不有意要冒犯上帝
Mind you, you've not been offending God.
但既然我已经警告你了 你现在就在冒犯他
But now you've been warned, and you'd offend Him now.
我愣愣地看着他
I looked at him distractedly.
他看起来又强壮又坚实
He's a strong and steady man.
一个名符其实的上帝的仆人 他正在勇敢地面对
A true servant of God. He too has faced up to it.
我们似乎在一条看不见的大路上
It was as if we were bidding farewell to each other
正在互相道别
across some invisible highway.
现在 你也不要再胡思乱想了
Above all, don't let your imagination run away with you.
我只有一句话
I've only one thing to say:
你依然是个很不错的小教士
You are a wonderful little priest in spite of everything.
我并不想重伤那位可怜的死去的女士
And with no malice to the poor woman who died -
请不要说了
Please don't.
是的 我们不要再谈论那件事了
You're right. We'll not speak of that.
现在 请开始好好工作
And now, work.
做些小事 一点点地来 不要心急
Do little things, from day to day, while you wait.
小事看起来无足轻重 但它们能带来安宁
Little things don't seem like much, but they bring peace.
还有 开始祈祷吧
And try to pray.
坚持祈祷
Persevere.
向圣母祈祷
Pray to the Holy Virgin.
她是人类的慈母
She is, of course, the mother of mankind,
但也是天主的女儿
but she is also its daughter.
在旧世界 痛苦的世界里
The ancient world, the world before grace,
她在襁褓中摇晃着
rocked her in its cradle.
几个世纪 他都保护着
For centuries its old hands protected
这个奇妙的不知姓名的女孩
the wondrous young girl
whose name it didn't even know.
这个小女孩就是天使中的皇后
A little girl, this queen of the angels,
至今仍是 你不要忘记
which she still is to this day. Never forget that.
谢谢
Thank you.
请为我祝福
Give me your blessing.
不 应该由你来
No, it's your turn today.
给您 神父
Here you are, Father.
不 谢谢 我没事
No, thanks. Nothing.
会好的
It will pass.
这会让您很快好起来的
This will put you right again.
感觉好多了吗？
Feeling better?
好多了 谢谢
Much better, thank you.
我得回家了
I should have gone home.
我的胃稍微好了点 但我觉得有些晕眩
My stomach hurt less. I just felt a slight dizziness.
我一定是树林里晕倒了
I must have fainted the first time
beyond the Auchy woods.
在我意识中 我努力挣扎着要起来
I thought I was still struggling upright,
然而我只能感到脸颊触碰着冰冷的土地
and yet I could feel the frozen earth against my cheek.
"他们会看到我这样半死不活的" 我想道  "又会引起新的流言"
"They'll find me half dead, " I thought. Yet another scandal.
我想我开始呼救了起来
I think I called out.
我可怜的脑袋已经无法忍受这种痛苦了
My poor head couldn't stand it anymore.
托西神父所描绘的圣母形象
The image of the Holy Virgin as described by the priest
清晰地出现在我的面前
was constantly before me.
崇高的女人 她的双手
A sublime creature. Her hands -
我正紧紧盯着她的手看
I stared at her hands.
它们时而出现 时而消失
Now I'd see them, now they'd disappear.
我的痛苦几乎达到了顶点
As my pain grew more extreme,
我抓住其中的一只 攥入我的手心
I took one of them in mine.
那是一只贫苦孩子的手
It was the hand of a poor child,
一只因为辛勤劳作而变得粗糙的手
already roughened by hard work and washing.
饿闭上了眼睛
I closed my eyes.
重新睁开眼睛的时候 我几乎害怕
I feared, when opening them again,
看到那张脸 所有人都对着那张脸屈膝下跪
to see the face before which every knee must bend.
我看到了它
I saw him.
那一张毫无光泽的孩子的面孔
It was a child's face, without the slightest radiance.
我是在水塘里打的水 那里的水比较让人放心
I filled it at the pond. It seemed safer.
他们都在房子里
They're all there in the house.
我出来把奶牛们牵回厩的
I had gone out to bring the cows in.
您不该让自己变成现在这样的
You shouldn't let yourself get in such a state!
幸好我碰见了您
It's lucky I found you.
我以为您已经死了
I thought you were dead.
我得起来    你现在这样哪儿也去不了
- I have to get up. - You can't go home looking like that.
我怎么了？
What's wrong with me?
你呕吐了
You've vomited.
吐得满脸都是 我想你是不是吃了什么浆果
It's smeared all over your face as if you'd been eating black berries.
你在发抖 让我来吧 我习惯了
You're shaking. Let me do it. I'm used to it.
哎呀 又来了 和上星期在婚礼上做同样的事
My, my. Another thing entirely
from last week at the wedding!
明天到我的住所来
Come to the rectory tomorrow.
我会好好解释的
I'll explain.
上帝啊 不要这样
Heavens, no!
我说了您太多坏话
I've said too many awful things about you.
糟糕的话
Terrible things.
我知道您没有恶意
I know you didn't do this on purpose.
他们也许在您的酒里放了些什么
They probably put some powder in your glass.
他们那样做是闹着玩
They do things like that for fun.
不过幸好这次有我在 他们不会得逞了
But thanks to me, they won't have their fun this time.
我陪您走完这段路
I'll take you as far as the road.
快回家吧
Hurry home now.
我昨晚做梦梦到您了 您看起来很可怜
I had a dream about you last night. You looked miserable.
我醒来后都哭了
I woke up crying.
布料硬邦邦的 水也变成了红色
The cloth was stiff, and the water had turned red.
我意识到我流了许多血
I realized I'd lost a lot of blood.
我惊恐极了 死亡几乎随时将至
I was so surprised- fear of death came only later -
我决定乘一早的火车去里尔
that I decided to take the first train to Lille in the morning.
公鸡打鸣后 我醒了过来 感到好多了
At the cock's crow, I woke feeling fine.
又吐了一阵血
Another bit of hemorrhaging. More like spitting blood.
我害怕死亡
Fear of death.
感觉像是我整个身体正围绕着胸口的一个点颤动着 非常奇怪
Strange how my whole body seems
to quiver around one point in my breast.
黎明对我来说简直太过美好
Dawn is always so sweet to me.
祝福这美好的早晨！
Bless mornings!
我开始祈祷
I pray better.
我听说您明早就要离开了
You're going away tomorrow, I hear.
是的
Yes.
您还会回来吗？
Will you be coming back?
要看情况
That depends.
由您自己决定？
It depends... on you?
由我在里尔的医生决定
On the doctor I'm to see in Lille.
我想
I thought -
那是奥利佛的摩托车
That's Olivier's motorcycle.
我的表兄
My cousin.
请来帮帮我
Help me
既然您现在在这里
as long as you're here -
尽管这违背您父亲的意思 我还是要这样要求您
against your father's will, I might add.
您当然可以有所保留
You sure keep your cards hidden.
我能问问您是怎么看待我的吗？
May I ask what you think of me?
神父是不能提出对个人的见解的
A priest has no opinions.
但你能看到我 也能听到我You have eyes and ears
您也像任何普通人一样了解我
and make use of them like everyone else, I suppose.
我并没有了解到任何东西
They would tell me nothing about you.
为什么？
Why not?
您总是如此不安
You're always restless,
企图隐瞒您内心所想
hoping to conceal the truth of your soul
或者干脆忘了它
or perhaps to forget it.
我不害怕真理
I'm not afraid of the truth.
你要是敢打我
And if you're daring me -
我不是要打你
I'm not daring you.
除非你遇到了死亡的威胁 我才会倾听你的忏悔
I'd only agree to hear your confession
if you were in danger of death.
我想 赦免也会很快
Absolution will come in due time, I hope,
通过他人降临的
and from someone else's hand.
您没什么可掩藏的
That wasn't hard to predict.
上帝马上就会将您调离这里
Father will be sure to have you transferred.
在这儿 所有人都认为你是个酒鬼
Everyone here takes you for a drunkard.
如果您仅仅想知道我对生命的看法
If you only knew what I think of life.
在我生命中 所有的东西我都想得到 我也一定会努力得到它们
I want everything. I'll try everything.
我知道许多人到死都没能做到
I know plenty of others have died
without managing to do that.
如果生命让我无法得偿所愿 那就这样吧
If life disappoints me, so be it.
我会为了罪恶而罪恶的
I will sin just for sin's sake.
那时候上帝就会来带走你
That's the moment you'll find God.
我想狠狠地侮辱您一番
I feel like -  don't know -insulting you!
您自认为能违背我的想法来断定我的命运？
You think you can decide my fate against my will?
如果我这样做 我会诅咒自己的
I'll damn myself if I please.
我是以灵魂来回答你的
I answer for you, soul for soul.
您刚才不是在说 究竟是什么撞碎了您的幻想吗？
Are you just saying whatever strikes your fancy?
您和我母亲说话的时候 我正巧在窗边听到了
I was at the window when you spoke with Mother.
突然之间 她说话变得那么温和
All ofa sudden, her expression became so gentle.
我并不相信鬼魂与奇迹的说法
I don't believe in miracles any more than I do in ghosts,
但我至少了解我的母亲
but I think I knew my mother.
她在意措辞就像鱼儿在意温度一样敏感
She cared for fine phrases like a fish cares for apples.
你们之间有什么秘密？
Do you have some secret?
我不想提起这个
A lost secret.
你太想找到它 反会失之交臂You too will find it and lose it in turn,
而其他人会在你身后将这个秘密传递下去
and others will pass it on after you.
神父 你到哪里去？
Where are you going, Father?
去马塞尔格乘火车
To Mazargues, to catch the train.
您有骑过摩托车吗？想试试看吗？
Ever ridden on one of these? Want to try?
来吧
Come on.
您不怕吗？
You're not frightened?
为何此时我感到奇迹般的年轻？
How could I feel so miraculously young then?
是的 就像我的同行者这样年轻
Yes, as young as my companion.
事情突然变得非常简单
Things suddenly seemed simple.
年轻人都是被祝福的
Youth is blessed.
你有权做冒险的事 甚至你做冒险的事都会被上帝祝福
It's a risk you take, and even that risk is blessed.
抓紧了！
Hold on!
我觉察到一种无法言明的征兆
By some premonition I can't explain,
我想 上帝并不希望我在还没
I understood that God didn't want me to die
尝试这种冒险之前就死去
without knowing something of this risk.
而当这个时刻到来时 我的献身也能功德圆满
just enough for my sacrifice to be complete when it's time came.
你就要走了 真是可惜 我还可以再载你一程的
Too bad you're leaving. We could have done this again.
我很喜欢你 我们能成为朋友的
I like you. We could have been friends.
我 成为你的朋友？
Me, your friend?
当然
Of course.
我知道你不是他们传言那样的人
Not that I haven't heard plenty about you.
我舅舅嘲笑你是个下贱又百无一用的小神父
My uncle thinks you're a filthy, good-for-nothing little priest.
我想你不会介意他怎么想吧
I don't suppose you care what he thinks.
你大概不知道 我投靠了国外的阵营
You probably don't know I'm in the Foreign Regiment.
阵营？
The Regiment?
我是说军队
The Legion, I mean.
如果你能看看自己的样子
If you could only see yourself.
看看我自己？
See myself?
你脱下身上的黑袍 和我们这些年轻人完全是一样的
Without that black robe, you'd look like any one of us.
我一眼就看出来了
I could see that right off the bat.
您不是这个意思
You don't mean it.
我正是这个意思
I certainly do.
什么？一个青年神父？
What? A priest?
我们那儿就有很多神父
There are plenty of priests out there.
我原来的指挥官先前就是个神父 之后我们才发现这一点
My major's orderly was one. We only found out afterwards.
之后？
Afterwards?
他阵亡之后
After his death.
他是怎么阵亡的？
How did he die?
死在了一头骡子身上 他像根香肠一样横在骡背上
On a mule, strung up like a sausage,
子弹打穿了他的腹部
a bullet through his belly.
我不是问这个
That's not what I meant.
听着 我不会对你撒谎的
Look, I won't lie to you.
这些家伙们死前都乐意好好炫耀一番
The guys like to show off when their time has come.
他们那种表达方式 你也许会称之为亵渎
They have an expression or two
you'd probably call blasphemy.
但上帝并没有拯救士兵们 且正是因为他们是士兵他才没有救他们
But if God doesn't save all soldiers
precisely because they're soldiers,
所以 尊敬又有什么用？
then what's the use?
多说句亵渎的话也无所谓 然后 砰
One more blasphemy for good measure, and then... bam.
道理是一样的 不成功便成仁
It's always the same motto: "All or nothing."
我敢打赌 就你来说
I bet you yourself-
我想我舅舅说你没什么社交能力是对的
You know, my uncle's right when he says
you have no social skills.
承认吧 我们的世界和他们的不一样
Admit it, our world isn't theirs.
我不排斥他们的世界
I don't reject theirs.
但他们的世界没有爱
But it lacks love.
我们这些年轻人不像你这么了解他们
Our chaps don't have your wisdom in the matter.
上帝不过代表他们所鄙视的正义
God seems to them to stand for a justice they despise -
这种正义对他们而言毫无荣耀
a justice without honor.
只有他们自己认定的法则才值得他们去努力
Their own law has the merit of costing a lot, an awful lot.
像个祭坛 他们赋予它意义
It's like a sacrificial altar.
其实它不过是块巨大的石块
Just a stone, no larger than any other.
拉维尼医生 医学院教授
DR. LAVIGNE    PROFESSOR, FACULTY OF MEDICINE
我径直向车站走去
I walked straight ahead toward the station.
半当中 我走进了一座不知名的教堂
I entered an old church. I didn't even know its name.
过去祈祷时 我从未感到身体动起来如此艰难
I'd never felt such a violent, physical revulsion to prayer.
即使我祈愿也无能为力
My will was helpless in the face of it.
这样您就能安心写您的布道词了
This way you can go on quietly writing your sermon.
我年轻的时候的那些神父们吃得可多了
When I was young, priests used to eat too much.
看看您 简直瘦得像只猫
Now you're as skinny as alley cats.
当然啦 刚开始总是很累人的
Beginnings are always hard.
别担心 您这个年纪 未来的日子还长着呢
Never mind. At your age you have your whole life before you.
我告诉自己应该冷静 我得保持沉默I knew to keep calm, I had to keep silent.
癌症
Cancer.
胃癌
Stomach cancer.
当这个词进入我的耳朵的时候 我觉得整个大脑都空了
The words had rung in my ears but left my mind empty.
我本以为会是肺结核
I had expected something else: tuberculosis.
但我只是皱了皱眉 就像听到了个并不太严重的问题似的
I think I just frowned, like when hearing of a difficult problem.
过了好久我似乎才能意识到 我很快就要因此死去了
It took me a long time to realize I was to die from a disease
在我这样的年纪 几乎是不会发生的
that rarely strikes people of my age.
杜普路易太太为我送来了杯黑咖啡后就离开了
She left me alone with a cup of black coffee.
我感觉并不太糟 甚至睡着了一小会儿
I felt well and even fell asleep for an instant.
当我醒来...
When I woke...
上帝 我必须将它写下来
God, I must write it down.
我想念前几天的早晨
I think of my last few mornings this week,
鸡鸣过后 窗外看起来如此平和
of the cock's crow and my peaceful window.
纯净 且生机勃勃！
How fresh and pure it all was!
尽管我努力告诉自己
Even though I kept telling myself
这几周里 我什么也没变
nothing had changed inside me over the last weeks,
这种渴望回家的念头...几乎使我感到羞愧
the idea of going home with this...thing... made me feel ashamed.
药物及相关
DRUGS AND SIMILAR PRODUCTS
阿伯特・迪福雷蒂是我被派往教区之前
Abbot Dufrety had studied with me at the seminary
在神学院的同窗好友
before being assigned to a small parish.
我知道他如今已经不再从事神职I knew he'd taken a leave from the ministry
据说只是因为生病而辞职的
only because of illness.
他只穿了件衬衫
He was in shirtsleeves,
下身穿着我们袍子下的棉裤
in those cotton pants we wear under our cassocks,
光着脚穿着拖鞋
and bare foot in his slippers.
你应该早点告诉我你要过来 我在镇上有个办公室
You might have let me know. I have an office in town.
我只是偶尔住这儿 这里真是太破了
I only camp out here. The place is disgusting.
我想多吃点 但我吃不进去
I'm supposed to eat a lot, but I don't have much appetite.
还记得在神学院吃的豆子吗
Remember those beans at the seminary?
这里更糟 烧菜都只能在这儿做
The worst is, the cooking has to be done right here.
只能忍着油烟味
I've taken a dislike to the smell of frying.
在别的地方 我会狼吞虎咽的
Anywhere else, I'd gobble up the stuff.
你来真是太好了
Nice of you to come.
老实说我吓了一跳
Frankly, I'm a bit surprised.
以前你有点想不太开
You used to be a bit narrow-minded in those days.
抱歉 我得去洗把脸
Excuse me. I'll just clean up a bit.
今天我过得很不错 这可不是常有的
I've had a good day, which doesn't happen often.
你还能期待什么呢？积极的生活足够好了
What do you expect? An active life is good for one.
但你不要以为我已经变得粗俗了
But don't think I've turned into an ignoramus.
我最近读了很多 从来没读得这么勤快过
I read voraciously. I've never read so much.
我这儿还有些笔记 等会儿给你看
I've got some notes here. I'll show you.
希望你留下来吃个晚饭 我们能好好聊聊
I hope you'll stay for dinner. We can have a nice chat.
怎么了？
What's the matter?
来 把它喝下去
Here, drink this.
你能怎么办？我们血管中流淌的血液就已经腐坏
What do you expect? We've got rotten blood in our veins.
一个医生曾对我说过 "知识分子从小就营养不良！"
A doctor told me once, "Intellectuals, undernourished since childhood!"
这很有道理 你说呢？
Explains a lot, don't you think?
别以为我只是在为自己找借口
Don't think I'm just making excuses for myself.
我非常相信这个说法
I believe in utter honesty,
无论对他人还是对我自己都是对的
with others and with myself.
出疗养院后 我就想着要锻炼自己
When I left the sanatorium, I wanted to test myself.
所以我找了工作
I looked for a job.
但我意志和胆量都不够
It was a question of willpower and guts. Guts, mostly.
提醒你 我并不是要你学我这样做
Mind you, I'm not telling anyone to follow me.
我经历了非常痛苦的日子才缓了过来
There are bad times.
这期间 倘若我忘了对为我牺牲的人
And if it hadn't been for a feeling of responsibility
本应有的那些责任感的话...
towards someone who sacrificed her life for me -
好吧 这个事情是纯粹客观的
Well, we can talk about that quite objectively.
她对我没有任何索求
She counts for nothing in my intellectual life.
别觉得太惊奇 别感到困惑 ！
And don't think it was a bolt
from the blue, a bewilderment!
你惊讶吗？
You're surprised?
没有
No.
但以你这样的处境
But in your place,
倘若我必须违背我在接受神职时作出的宣誓
if I'd broken my ordination promises,
我情愿那是因为对一个女人的爱情
I'd rather it had been for love of a woman,
而不是你所说的客观的理性的生活
than for what you call your intellectual life.
我不同意你的说法
I don't agree.
你不知道你在说些什么
You don't know what you're talking about.
我的理性生活
My intellectual life -
你怎么了？
What's the matter?
回答我！
Answer!
我不想死在这儿！
I don't want to die here!
让我离开，到哪儿去都行！
Get me out of here, anywhere!
我能怎么办？
What can I do?
我一个人搬不动他
I can't carry him by myself,
我们也不能叫看门人来帮忙
and we can't ask the concierge for anything.
别动 神父先生
Don't move, Father.
会好的
It will pass.
迪福雷蒂先生有些惊慌 他先去药店了
Mr. Dufrety panicked a bit and ran off to the pharmacy.
您对我的看法也许很糟糕
I'm afraid you must think poorly of me.
房间又脏又乱 没人打理
The room isn't tidied up and everything's dirty.
我每天五点就去上班
You see, I leave to work at 5:00 in the morning,
我已经没力气去做这些家务活了
and I just don't have the strength anymore.
您做什么工作？
What is your work?
我是个清洁工
I'm a cleaning lady.
最累的就是要从一个地方扫到另一个地方
The most tiring part is rushing from one place to another.
他的生意如何？
But what about his business?
他们说那儿有钱可赚
They say there's money in it,
但他借钱来置办办公室和打字机
but he had to borrow for the office and the typewriter.
他没法回避这些事
Besides, he can't get around much.
你们结婚了吗？
Are you married?
没有
No.
是我反对结婚的
I was the one against it.
为什么？
Why?
因为他就是这样的人 您难道没有看出来吗？
Because of what he is, don't you see?
在疗养院的时候我希望他能好起来
I always hoped he'd get well at the sanatorium.
所以 倘若他想要重新开始生活
And then, if he ever wanted to make a fresh start,
我绝不会挡他的路
I wouldn't be in the way, I told myself.
他是怎么想的？
And what did he think of that?
没什么
Nothing.
他只是以为我不想结婚
He thought I didn't want to.
您为什么要问这些？
Why do you ask?
出于友谊
Out of friendship.
药剂师是对的 他刚刚嘲笑了我
The pharmacist was right. He just laughed at me.
说真的 一次小小的昏厥都会吓到我
It's true: The smallest fainting spell terrifies me.
听着
Listen.
我得和你谈谈
I must talk to you.
时间不多了
There's little time.
和我谈什么？谈谁？
Talk to me about what? About whom?
你
You.
"他同意去见托西神父"
"He's agreed to meet with the priest in Torcy.
我的老院长
My old master -"
凌晨四点左右 我仍无法入睡 便去了他的房间
Around 4:00, unable to sleep, I went to his room
发现我可怜的同窗躺在了地上 不省人事
and found my poor colleague unconscious on the floor.
我们将他搬回床上
We carried him back to bed,
他吐了大量的血
where upon he vomited up streams of blood.
然后他渐渐停止吐血了
But the hemorrhaging ended.
当我们等待医生到来时 我可怜的朋友依稀恢复了知觉
While we waited for the doctor, our poor friend regained consciousness,
但他没有说话
but he didn't speak.
豆大的汗珠布满了他的眉间与双颊
Heavy beads ofsweat covered his brow and cheeks,
脸上的表情显得非常痛苦
and his expression told of great anguish.
他的脉搏逐渐变得愈加虚弱
His pulse was rapidly growing weak.
他示意他想要他的念珠
He motioned that he wanted his rosary,
我在他的裤子口袋里找到了它
which I found in his pants 'pocket.
他将念珠紧紧贴住胸口
From then on, he held it pressed against his chest.
看上去恢复了些许力气
He seemed to recover some strength
以几乎听不见的声音 请求着宽恕
and in an almost inaudible voice asked for absolution.
他的脸变得平和了 甚至发出了微笑
His face grew calm. He even smiled.
尽管无论出自人性还是出自友情我都应该拒绝他
Though neither humanity nor friendship would permit me to refuse,
要求我作为神父履行他的要求
while discharging my duties, I explained to my unfortunate comrade
我告诉了他我的犹豫
my hesitation at granting his request.
他似乎并没有听见
He didn 't seem to hear me.
然而过了一会儿 他将他的手放在我手上
But a few moments later, he laid his hands on mine
眼神示意着我上前去
while his eyes entreated me to draw closer to him.
他非常清晰地
He then said, very distinctly,
用极其缓慢的语调if extremely slowly,
一字一句地说道
these exact words:
"有什么关系？一切都是恩典"
"What does it matter? All is grace. "
我想 这之后 他就去世了
I believe he died just then.
个人翻译 annie